Good morning, today's דף daf is ק"ג. kof gimal. We pick up
with the right after the משנה mishnah on ק"ב ע"ב. kof bais
amud bais. I should mention that we're starting the seventh פרק, perek,
which is, in a way, this פרק perek is going to be
like the last of a group of פרקים. perakim. Just to step
back for a second and get a sort of bird's eye view,
you know the first two פרקים prokim of the מסכתא masechta were
about neighbors and building walls and privacy and doing things
in your yard that damage that you know could sort of encroach
upon the other person's rights and so on. So that was like
the whole first those two were like a unit around neighbors. The
third פרק perek was all about the idea of חזקה, chazaka, being
on land for three years and that giving you a claim to
the land, backing up your claim to the land, I should say.
And then the fourth, fifth, and sixth פרקים prokim were all about
selling and when you sell certain things what's included, how do you
do certain acts of taking possession, right, all about those sort of
issues about מקח טעות, mekach tos, if you say one thing and
deliver another. So those are all about those acts of transaction and
this is going to be the last of that of the buying
and the selling. And then the last section of the מסכתא, masechta,
eight, nine, and ten actually—I'm sorry, not seven, eight—eight, nine, and ten
are going to all be about death and about death and inheritance
and bequests and who inherits and writing wills and rabbinic forms of
wills. Okay, so it's going to be, in a few days we're
going to be starting a significantly different part of this מסכתא masechta
that really is disconnected. So there's like a few sections; we're in
this third section of these three פרקים prokim about buying and selling,
and then there's one very significant section at the end that's going
to be significantly different. Okay, so now we pick up with the
משנה mishnah on the bottom of ק"ב ע"ב. kof bais amud bais.
That's eight,
nine, and ten. We're in seven. Seven is the last of the
פרקים prokim about buying and selling. Okay, so the משנה mishnah started
with: if you say somebody's selling a בית כור, beis kor, which
is—that got erased—but anyway, it's 30 סאה. se'ah. We said that a
סאה se'ah was 5,000 square feet, so 30 סאה se'ah is 30
times that. So 5,000 square feet, I realized, is about 500 square
yards. The reason I'm thinking about that is because a football field
is 100 yards across, right? How wide is a football field? Anybody
knows? Is it like 10 yards? 20 yards? 20 yards maybe? I
think so. We'll just make that up. So let's say that a
football field is 2,000 square yards, and so this is 3,000 square
yards, a בית כור, beis kor, okay, if I'm doing the math
right in my head. Oh no, it's 1,500 square yards. This is—yes,
53 and a third yards—wide? Four acres? Okay, I don't know, I'm
thinking in football fields. Anyway,
it's about—it's 5,000—a בית סאה beis sa is 5,000 square feet, okay,
which divide by 9 is approximately 500 or whatever, 600 square yards,
okay. And if a football field is 100 by 20, which I'm
just making up the 20, that's 2,000.
So anyway, and
so a בית כור beis kor is 30 בית סאה, beis sa,
which
is 18,000 square yards, okay. And what did you say that a
football field was?
53 and a third? Let's call it 50 by 100, 5,000. So
that's about three and a half football fields. Okay. Three and a
half football fields, and somebody said it's about four acres, okay. So
that's a בית כור beis kor is 30 בית סאה. beis sa.
So that's like four acres, or what did I just say, how
many football fields? Three and a half football fields. Okay, so that's
the size we're talking about, if that gives you something. I think
I'm doing that right anyway.
Yes. Somebody has a note says that the size of the חצר
chatzer of the משכן mishkan was 5,000 square—right,
right, that's why
this—not 5,000, 50 by 100 square אמות, amos, which is
5,000 square אמות—50 amos by 100.
Oh, the משכן, mishkan, right. But that's two בית סאה. beis sa.
This is right, one בית סאה beis sa is half of that.
Okay, yes.
Anyway, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, let's continue with
it, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, or at least sometimes US football fields. US football fields.
Oh, it's also all in feet. It's in US measurement. Okay, anyway,
alright, moving on. Okay, anyway, so it's a large—it's a large space.
Now,
so somebody says they're selling that space, and the משנה mishnah said
that if there are in that space certain high rocks or crevices
that are ten טפחים tfachim high or higher, or ten טפחים tfachim
deep or deeper—ten טפחים tfachim is about 30 inches, a little bit
more, whatever, three feet,
okay—then those do not get counted in the land area. So you
would sort of, if there's a rock that's that big, then you'd
have to actually add on more land area. in order to have
to compensate for that space. And the רשב״ם Rashbam says that it's
he added it's not just ten טפחים tefachim high or deep, but
it's also what's the width and length? So he said four by
four. I actually yesterday mistakenly said four אמות amot by four אמות.
amot. He actually meant four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים. tefachim. I
got confused because the first thing I look at when people give
dimensions and they often don't bother to tell you what what do
you call it what you know measurement they're talking about is if
it's in if it's in masculine or feminine. So this is ארבעה
טפחים arba'ah tefachim and this is ארבע אמות. arba amot. So he
wrote ארבע arba but he meant ארבעה arba'ah because he said what
I missed was that he said that he's dealing with the dimensions
of a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. A private domain for שבת Shabbat
is four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים, tefachim, which is about a
foot by a foot by ten טפחים tefachim high, about three feet
high, okay?
Three three feet high. A foot by a foot by about three
feet, four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim by ten טפחים. tefachim.
That's considered a private domain by שבת Shabbat if it's surrounded by
walls. So the very fact that that's defined as a private domain
if it's and also a private domain would be even without walls
if something was ten טפחים tefachim high and four טפחים tefachim by
four טפחים. tefachim. So the top of this rock would be a
private domain or the bottom of that crevice would be a private
domain. The bottom of the crevice actually would have walls around it,
the walls would be the walls of the crevice. So that really
makes a lot of sense. If this type of a rock or
crevice or whatever is essentially for שבת Shabbat considered a separate domain,
so then it's not counted in the land area. And therefore you
have to give the person you know other land in order to
compensate for that. That doesn't get counted in the בית סאה. beit
se'ah. What I don't what is not explicit here is that who
owns that rock? I mean and I'm very serious about this like
is it like okay we don't count it in the land area
I'll give you more land but that's still my rock you know
that's still my crevice. Let's say they find oil under the rock.
No I'm serious you know!
Exactly! So is it just like you get the rock because it's
in the middle of the whole yard but you know but I
didn't give you enough tillable land so I have to make up
for that or is it no then that's not sold it's a
separate place and because it's a separate place it's not included in
the sale? Logically I would say the latter. If it's its own
separate place and that's why I have to give you more land
then it wasn't part of the land that I sold you. Yes
טוב. tov.
Why is the height of the rock in this kind of is
it I assume it's because of as you said tillable land? Right.
So if there's a short rock there you can't really till it.
Right. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say like you know
there's also just realities no land is perfect. So like you know
so we accept the fact that there are going to be bumps
and crevices and so on. I'm not promising you completely flat land
you know or that every square inch is tillable. But like something
that creates...
the height of the rock...
because well first of all if first of all
I mean let's see in the גמרא Gemara because the גמרא Gemara
is going to deal with whether it's tillable or not so let's
get back to that okay? Let's start the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this תנן התם. tnan hatam. Now I want
now I want to get started hold on one second. תנן התם.
tnan hatam. So we taught over there. So this is our משנה
Mishnah about whether it's you know included in the measurements of the
land. So we taught over
there המקדיש שדהו בשנת היובל Hamakdish sadeh bishnat hayovel somebody sanctifies his
field to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Now this literally
says בשנת היובל bishnat hayovel or בשעת היובל bishat hayovel it says
בשנת היובל. bishnat hayovel. But the reason בשנת היובל bishnat hayovel doesn't
work is because if you sanctify something during the יובל Yovel it
doesn't get to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash it like immediately reverts
to you. Right you sanctify your field when the יובל Yovel runs
around the field reverts to you. So you can't if you try
to sanctify your field during the time of during the year of
the יובל Yovel it would like immediately revert it wouldn't be a
relevant a relevant like discussion. So the רשב״ם Rashbam switches the גרסא
girsa to not בשנת היובל bishnat hayovel but בשעת היובל bishat hayovel
at the time when in history when the יובל Yovel was was
applying.
My גמרא Gemara says בשעת היובל.
bishat hayovel. I know because it follows the רשב״ם Rashbam okay? Because
at the time of history when we had the יובל Yovel first
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash maybe second בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash is very
debatable. Anyway at a time when the יובל Yovel was relevant. תוספות
Tosafot says no בשנת היובל bishnat hayovel could mean immediately after the
יובל Yovel it doesn't have to mean during the יובל Yovel year
itself. Okay so anyway you sanctified your field during this period of
the יובל Yovel maybe immediately after the יובל Yovel was over נותן
לו לבית זרע חומר שעורים חמישים שקל כסף. noten lo leveit zera
chomer se'orim chamishim shekel kasef. This is what the תורה Torah says.
For every area of field that is to the amount that you
could plant a seed of a חומר שעורים chomer se'orim of this
certain quantity of seed so it's fifty שקל כסף. shekel kasef. That's
what the תורה Torah says. Now that actual area is guess what?
A בית כור. beit kor. Okay it's the same as the Rabbinic
בית כור. beit kor. So for a Rabbinic בית כור beit kor
what the תורה Torah says is you sanctify your field you want
to buy it back from the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash so you
don't go by its market value you go by the fixed value
in the תורה. Torah. If it is basically you know if it's
like a you know if it's a type of a of a
plantable field. So that's fifty כסף kasef for the forty-nine years that's
assuming you sanctify the the first year of the יובל, Yovel, because
then it can produce for forty-nine years. It's going to revert to
you on the יובל, Yovel, right? If you sanctified it at, if
you sanctified it, like, with thirty years to go or you waited
twenty years to redeem it, then you would be able to buy
it back at a pro-rated amount. Okay, but if you want to
sort of buy it back right now, redeem it right now, it's
fifty שקל shekel for this בית כור. Beit Kor. היו שם נקיעים
עמוקים עשרה טפחים או סלעים גבוהים עשרה טפחים. Hayu sham nekaim amukim
asara tfachim o slain gvohim asara tfachim. Now it has the exact
same point that we do about what, how do you measure this
land in order to figure out how much you have to redeem
it for? Okay, so it says, if you, so if there were
these rocks that were ten or these crevices that were ten, אין
נמדדין עמה, ein nmdadin imah, they are not measured with it.
Okay, so you don't use them at all?
Like how does that work? So, that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to ask, because does that mean they weren't sanctified, does that
mean they get redeemed at a different rate? Okay, so we're going
to take a look at that right now, okay?
So, just one minute,
so okay, so it says, so the גמרא Gemara says now, ואמאי,
v'amai, okay I'm sorry, פחות מכאן נמדדין עמה. pachos mikan nmdadin imah.
Less than that it is measured with it. So the גמרא Gemara
says ואמאי? v'amai? So why is this true that they're not sanctified
with it? לקדשו באנפי נפשיהו. likdishu b'anpei nafshaihu. Let them be קדוש
kadosh separately. Meaning, okay you want to say it's
a separate space, entity, it's not one with the field around it
because of its height or its depth, it's a separate unit. Fine.
So why should we say that it wasn't קדוש kadosh and you
were only
sanctifying the flat land of the field? You sanctified your entire field.
You said I'm sanctifying my field. You didn't say בית כור אני
מוכר לך Beit Kor ani mocher lacha where we would want to
say let's measure it, right? You said I'm sanctifying my entire field.
So this was sort of a little field within your larger field,
let's say, let's say they both became sanctified. So what difference should
it
make whether it's measured or not measured, let them both be sanctified.
Alright, so the
גמרא Gemara says whether it's one unit or two units, at the
end of the day you were sanctifying both of them. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, וכי תימא כיון דלא הוי בית כור
לא קדשי. v'chi teima keivan d'lo havei Beit Kor lo kadshi.
Now maybe you say wait, wait, maybe the תורה Torah only says
that only if something is this size is it קדוש. kadosh. Less
than this it's not sanctified at all. Now that's a pretty radical
possibility that it's not sanctified at all. The רשב"ם Rashbam says that
we don't really mean, I'm just let me just check the רשב"ם
Rashbam to make sure I'm saying this
correctly, yeah,
he says it doesn't mean literally that they're not sanctified, but it
means that they wouldn't follow the same rules. Because when the תורה
Torah says that when you sanctify a שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, like
a field of inheritance, it's redeemed at this rate, not at the
market rate, but it's fifty כסף kesef per בית כור, Beit Kor,
okay, that's only if it's a שדה אחוזה. sadeh achuza. If it's
a field of inheritance, if it's a field that you purchased, we'd
have a different rule. If it's not a field, if it's let's
say a courtyard or some other type or a house or something
like that, it would follow a different rule. Okay, so the question
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says is not that we're thinking that
it wouldn't be sanctified at all, but what he's saying is that
the גמרא Gemara is saying is like like let's say you want
to say that if it's less than a בית כור Beit Kor
it shouldn't follow this rule of this rate of redemption, that only
something that's a full בית כור Beit Kor is redeemed at this
rate of fifty שקל shekel per בית כור. Beit Kor. Smaller things,
maybe they would be redeemed at market rate. Okay, so that's what
the רשב"ם Rashbam says, I mean how he explains the גמרא. Gemara.
So let's see that again. וכי תימא כיון דלא הוי בית כור,
v'chi teima keivan d'lo havei Beit Kor, but you say listen, if
we consider this rock part of the בית כור, Beit Kor, it
follows the normal rate of redeeming שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, fifty שקל
shekel per בית כור. Beit Kor. But maybe the point of saying
that it's a separate entity is not to say that it's not
holy, it's not sanctified, but that it's sanctified and because it's such
a small place, it doesn't follow the redemption rates of the בית
כור. Beit Kor. So if you say that, לא קדשי, lo kadshi,
meaning not that it's not sanctified at all, but it doesn't follow
the same rates of redemption. והתניא שדה. v'ha tanya sadeh. It says
it says if you, this is quoting the פסוק, pasuk, if you
sanctify a field. מה תלמוד לומר, mah talmud lomar, why does it
say a field? לפי שנאמר זרע חומר שעורים בחמישים שקל כסף, lefi
shene'emar zera chomer seorim bachamishim shekel kesef, that this amount of seed
of land that can be seeded this amount is for fifty שקל.
shekel. אין לי אלא שהקדיש כעניין זה, ein li ela shehikdish ke'inyan
zeh, maybe these rules of this rate of redemption is only if
you sanctify something this large. מנין לרבות לתך וחצי לתך סאה תרקב
וחצי תרקב? minayin l'rabos lesech v'chatzi lesech se'ah tarka v'chatzi tarka? How
do you know to include even much smaller parcels of land? Those
are different sizes of area.
תלמוד לומר שדה מכל מקום.
talmud
lomar sadeh mikol makom.
Any type of field.
So any field that's a שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, it's limited to
שדה אחוזה, sadeh achuza, right, it wouldn't apply to it wouldn't apply
to something that is not tillable land, you know, something that's like
whatever, not a land for growing, but like your courtyard, it won't
apply to something that you bought. Okay, but any field that is
a שדה אחוזה sadeh achuza follows this rate and it's proportional to
the size. So the גמרא Gemara is saying so what is the
point of the משנה? mishnah? says, I go and I stand in
my field and I say I am sanctifying this field to הקדש
Hekdesh and there is a big rock there or a big crevice
or whatever it is or a big mound. Okay, so okay, call
it a different field, it's going to be redeemed at the same
rate. What difference does it make whether it's measured together with it
or not? So now you have one thing of forty-nine units and
one of one unit, as opposed to one big thing of fifty
units. They're all redeemed at the same rate. So what's the difference?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so אמר רב עוקבא בר חמא, Amar
Rav Ukva bar Chama, הכא בנקעים מלאים מים עסקינן, hacha binkaim mele'im
mayim askinan, דלאו בני זריעה נינהו. dilav bnei zriah ninhu. Ah,
so I was sort of giving it away a little because he
says, no, that only works if the stuff is tillable, the separate
unit. But if you've got a rock or if you've got a
crevice that you can't go into the crevice and actually plant in
it, it's filled with water, so it's not tillable land. So if
you sanctify, if I have a dirt lot outside of the city
and I sanctify it, it doesn't go by this rule of the
fifty שקל shekel for a certain size. That applies to a שדה
אחוזה. Sdei Achuza. Okay, that applies to something that is actually used
for growing produce. Something that is not tillable does not follow this
rate. So therefore, if the rock is not part of the sanctity
of the field and it's a separate unit, how much do I
redeem
this rock here for? How much do I redeem this crevice that's
not tillable for? So that goes by the market
rate, that does not go by the official rate in the תורה.
Torah. Let me just read one more sentence and take the question.
הכא בנקעים מלאים מים עסקינן, hacha binkaim mele'im mayim askinan, דלאו בני
זריעה נינהו, dilav bnei zriah ninhu, דיקא נמי דקתני דומיא דסלעים, deika
nami dkatani dumya d'sla'im, שמע מינה. shma mina. So therefore, it's similar
to, it also said rocks. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, אי הכי אפילו פחות מכאן נמי. Ei hachi afilu pachos
mikan nami. So then if even if my field was... so basically
what did I do?
I sanctified this field, okay, this was a בית כור, Beis Kor,
and the תורה Torah says it's going to be fifty שקל shekel
for me to redeem it if I redeem it at the beginning
of the יובל Yovel cycle. In the middle here there was this
big rock. So the first thing that the גמרא Gemara says is,
and let's say this
was forty-nine units or whatever. Okay, a בית כור Beis Kor is
thirty סאה. Seah. So let's say this is twenty-nine סאה Seah big
and this rock is one סאה Seah big. Okay, so the first
thing the גמרא Gemara said is, okay, big deal. So now you've
separated it, it's a separate unit, יישר כח. yasher koach. So now
this is, the twenty-nine units are redeemed at the rate of fifty
שקל shekel per בית כור Beis Kor and the one unit is
redeemed at the rate of fifty שקל shekel per בית כור. Beis
Kor. What do I care if I call them two units or
one unit? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, no. This is not
plantable. So since this is not plantable, it's a rock or it's
a crevice that's filled with water, so the twenty-nine units are redeemed
at the rate of fifty שקל shekel per בית כור, Beis Kor,
so this you'd divide by twenty-nine thirtieths. Okay, that would be redeemed
at that rate. And this would be redeemed at the market rate.
Since this is a separate unit, so you say it's like I
sanctified a rocky land to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. If you
sanctify rocky land to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it doesn't go
by this rate. This rate is for tillable land. So how, what
rate does it go by? It goes by whatever the market rate
is. So this goes by this rate and this goes by the
market rate because it's a separate unit. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, so then even if it wasn't a separate unit, let's say
it was a shorter rock, it was a smaller rock. Okay, why
does it go by this rate? It's not tillable. So the answer
is pretty obvious as the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, ei hachi,
says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, אפילו פחות מכאן נמי, afilu
pachos mikan nami, even if the rock is smaller, is not as
high, is whatever. So if it's not tillable, it should be going
by a different rate. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. הנך נגני
דארעא מקרו, Hani nigni d'ara mikru, שדרי דארעא מקרו. shadrei d'ara mikru.
Those are called like bumps in the land, those are called little
dips in the land. Those are not seen as separate. You don't...
yeah, they're part of it. Like you don't go ahead and measure
every little square inch of land and say, wait, wait, that inch
is there's a rock there, it's rocky, it's not tillable, we're going
to have to deduct that, whatever. Which is similar to the logic
in our משנה. Mishna. If it's a small thing, you say, okay,
the land as a whole unit is tillable, it goes by this
rate. But once it defines its own space, then you're saying, okay,
it's not, you can't say the land as a whole. Here's a
significant space that's its own unit that's not tillable and therefore that's
going to go as a different rate. Okay, so that's the logic
of that, and that of course feeds into our משנה. Mishna. If
I sell you a whole big plot of land and there's a
small like low thing, a small
thing that's not tillable, that's a bump, it's like okay, that's whatever,
it's part of the land, the land has bumps. But if it
defines its own space, then it's like that's not part of what
I'm selling you.
Yeah, that's what I was going to get you, like in terms
of tillable,
there's tillable and then there's like hard earth that, you know what
I mean?
Right, hard scrabble.
Yeah, and given the hard scrabble,
what kind of quality?
Yeah, so that's
true. Meaning, none of this talks about, I mean obviously when, if
I'm selling it to you, you're hoping to get land that's of
good quality. But if I mean it's an interesting question between the
difference between the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and me selling it to
you. Because here what
you know, it's a
it's a good point because right, it seems like you need both
things, right? If it's like, if it's just stuff that is not
high and not deep or whatever, then it's by, you know, it's
it seems like it's part of the land, even if it's, you
know, so I I'm just trying to process this. So let's say
I sanctified this land to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Like if I sanctified, if I sanctified a land outside you had
a nice beautiful wheat field. Right next, everybody has these wheat fields.
I with my luck got the exact got an acre that's all
like complete rock, not tillable at all, right? So and I sanctified
it to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's not it would not
go by this rate. It's not tillable land. So if I sanctify
like, you know, an acre that is tillable with a big section
that's not, why does it have to be high or low? If,
like, you would think basically what you're saying is, is that if
it's wide enough, if it's large enough in area, right, that should
be make it its sort of own space, like sort of different
than if it's like high or low, and it's not like בטל
batel to the whole space.
But also I'm just wondering like what happens, you know, you want
to buy a כור kor and I give you the permafrost in
Alaska. Doesn't do you much good but it's like, you know, it's
not rock. You know what I mean? Like, you know, then what?
Do you have a טענה ta'ana against me?
Right. So
yeah, I mean I think that that's a good point. I think
you're right. I mean I think it's the same point, I have
to think about it, but I think that the point is what
allows small untillable spaces is the fact that they are בטל batel
in the majority, right? If it is a actually I don't know
why I'm why I'm struggling so much. It's coming up in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, I just didn't sort of I'm not just connecting
what you're saying to what the גמרא Gemara is saying. But the
גמרא Gemara is going to say that if the area is big
enough, then it doesn't matter how high or low it is. Then
it stands by itself and it's not בטל. batel. If it's a
small amount of area, then it only stands by itself if it's
high or low.
Right. If you have a big enough area of really bad land,
you'd have a טענה ta'ana against me.
Exactly. Okay, and we're going to get to that in the גמרא.
Gemara. I just wasn't processing it.
I mean I think we should think about it as a linguistic
thing as the גמרא Gemara does. You know, this is called a
field even though it has parts of it that are, you know,
not tillable. And this, which is above a certain size thing, is
not a field. It was not this is the field and this
is the rock. Right, right. So, you know, trying to parse exactly
how much is tillable and how much is not tillable is not
that's not the issue. The issue is what's called a field.
Right. But the גמרא Gemara is going to get to the the
point that Michael made and he's correct, meaning if you have a
small amount of spaces, what defines them as not I mean if
you want to sort of use this term a little imprecisely, but
בטל batel to the rest of the field, like okay, the field
has bumps or whatever, we can't worry about every square inch, you
know, that's so when do we say that, if it's a you
know, when does it stop being just integrated into the larger field
and stand by itself? Either if it's, you know, very high or
very low, or as we're going to see, which is what Michael's
asking, if it's a significant amount of area. Once you're dealing with
a significant amount of area, right, so then obviously you can't just
say, 'Okay, you know, I mean I'm selling you tillable land and
if there's a significant section that isn't tillable, it's not like every
land has its problems.' Yes.
So the extent I mean what the problem with the הקדש hekdesh
is that
you really care what is in it and not in it because
the rate is fixed. If it's not such good land, wouldn't a
buyer and seller agree on a price that reflects the quality of
the land?
Yeah, so you know what this sort of expects is that, like,
it would and like a lot of these questions is like why
didn't you just check it out beforehand? Why didn't you just more
specific? You know, sometimes we aren't or sometimes I go and I
look at the land and I look at a little part of
it and it looks really good and I'm whatever, I'm not an
astute buyer, and I say I'll buy a whole acre. And then
when I come to till it, I realize that, you know, I
didn't check every that there's a whole space here that's hard and
untillable, right? Or there's a big rock. I whatever, I didn't do
my due diligence. I didn't go ahead and I checked every inch,
you know, and here's whatever. So so you're right. Logically, they should
you should check out the whole thing and figure out an appropriate
price. But here the point is you didn't do that and now
I'm sort of saying like, I want you to give me more
land or give me some of my money back. I was expecting
it all to be tillable, right? And you say, 'Look, sometimes there
are problems,' you know. So the basic point is that when it
is significant enough, high or or low, or what Michael's asking, wide,
which we're going to see but we haven't seen yet, right, then
you can't say it's just a bump in the land. Then it's
like a separate unit and it really needs to be, you know,
compensated for. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. הכא
מאי. Hacha mai. Now we said that by the case of הקדש,
hekdesh, what makes it a separate unit was or what makes it
go by different rate was it was untillable. Because if you had
a big big mound but it was all tillable, we said big
deal. So you have, you know, one plot of land and another
plot of land and they're all redeemed by the same rate. Okay,
so it wouldn't have made a difference. We had to say it
was talking about not... But in this case when I'm selling something
to to to you and you've got a big mound, okay, it's
you're not happy with the big mound even if it is tillable
because you know your plow doesn't go straight over the mound. You
want flat land. Okay, you're not happy with a big crevice even
if you could somehow get down there and plant in it. You
want flat land. So here when it says, when we say if
you've got a mound or a crevice, you, it's, you know, if
it's deep enough, it's not included and you, you know, you make
it up with other land, so would that apply even if they
are tillable or only if they are like rocks? Okay, and I,
you know, so הכא מאי, Hacha mai, what's the story here? אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, אף על פי שאין מלאים מים. Af
al pi she'ein mele'im mayim. In this case, the crevice would not
be sold with the land and you'd have to make up for
it even if it's not filled with water. So מאי טעמא, Mai
ta'ama, why? איננו רוצה שיתן מעותיו במקום אחד ויהיו לו כשנים ושלשה
מקומות. Einenu rotzeh sheyiten me'otav bemakom echad veyihyu lo kishnayim ulishlosha mekomot.
I don't want to pay for one place and effectively have multiple
places. So I don't want to say, well, you know, you have
your whole acre, some's here, and some's here, and some's here, and
some's there, you know, I want one flat acre. So if I
have to, in order to get to my acre, I got to
go up on a mound, I don't want to do that. Give
me some more flat ground or, you know, give me back my
money. This doesn't count as part of my acre. I want an
acre of flat ground. So even if it's tillable, it's not included.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף לה רבינא ואיתימא דסלוין תני, Matkif
lah Ravina ve'aitima de-Slonim tani, but the משנה Mishna says rocks. So
if it says rocks, presumably we're talking about, you know, a non-tillable,
and for the same thing could be by a crevice if it
should be filled with water. So מה סלעים דלא בני זריעה נינהו
אף הני נמי דלא בני זריעה נינהו. Mah sla'im dela benei zeri'ah
ninhu af hanei nami dela benei zeri'ah ninhu. Same way rocks are
not tillable, the same should be about the crevices, and only then
is it not included. But if it's a bump, even if it's
tillable, even if it's a big bump, you have to deal with
it.
The משנה Mishna says no. כי תני דומיא דסלעים אפחות מכאן. Ki
tani dumya desla'im afachot mikan. No, no, no. The reason the משנה
Mishna said rocks was to tell me that if it's not ten
טפחים tefachim high, even if it's a rock, I have to, you
know, then you have to accept it. You know, land isn't perfect.
So what are we saying? So we're saying the following. We're saying
I go ahead and I sell you this acre, I'll call it
an acre. This acre of land, if you've got, you know, sections
that are not ten טפחים tefachim high, but they are, you know,
they're these little boulders, these little raised rocks or whatever, and you're
telling me, hey, I can't plant this, something, you know, whatever, what
the גמרא Gemara says. Every land has its bumps, every land has
its, has, you know, has its imperfections, so just live with it.
All right, but if you have something that's really big, ten טפחים
tefachim high, really deep, even if it's not a boulder, even if
it's tillable, then you're going to say to me, look, this is
really not just a little bump in the land, this is its
own place, and I was expecting one flat unit. I wasn't expecting,
you know, different types of units. So in that type of a
case, even if it is tillable, you know, I actually have to
give you a, give you a discount or give you other land
to make up for it. Okay, so that's the basic issue of
the משנה. Mishna. Now the גמרא Gemara deals with the question about
what if the area is too big. So אמר רב יצחק, Amar
Rav Yitzchak, טרשים שאמרו בית ארבעת קבין. Terashim she'amru beit arba'at kabin.
When we said that if you have these mounds, that they are,
how they, that they are, or these rocks, that they are not
a problem if they're less than ten טפחים tefachim high, that's only
if they do not exceed four קב kav to a בית סאה.
beit se'ah. Okay, now what's four קב kav to a בית סאה?
beit se'ah? So a קב kav is there are six קב, kav,
I'm sorry, four קבין kabin to a בית כור. beit kor. So
there are six
קבין kabin to a סאה. se'ah.
So four קבין, kabin, so and there are thirty סאה se'ah to
a בית כור. beit kor. Okay, so and there are thirty סאה
se'ah
to a בית כור. beit kor.
So four קבין kabin in a בית כור beit kor would be,
what is it?
There
are 180 קב, kav, wait a minute, there are 180 קב kav
in a בית כור. beit kor. So four, four out of 180
is two out of 90 is 1/45th. I think I did that
right.
Okay, so only four קב kav in the entire place, it's about
1/45th of the place. Did I do that right? Is that what
it says in the footnote? 1/45th, wonderful. Okay, all
right, so right, a little more than 2%. Only up to four
קב kav of these rocks, even if they're low, even if they're
not high.
Okay, but if they're more than that, so this is exactly the
question Michael's asking. If they're more than that, then you didn't sell,
then, you know, a certain, the majority, the 90, like, you know,
I bought tillable land. So if you're selling me here more than,
you know, more than four קבין kabin of this land is not
tillable, I don't care for the separate space or not a separate
space, like, you know, you're giving me my money back for that.
That's too much.
So ואמר רב עוקבא בר חמא, Ve'amar Rav Ukva bar Chama, והוא
שמובלעים בחמשה קבין. vehu shemuvla'im bechamisha kabin. But you know what he
says? Actually not so fast.
a problem. You know, but if they're condensed in a small space,
in the space of five קב, kav, meaning they're all together, right?
That's when it's like one unit and that's when it is a
problem. So what it's basically saying is you might not need height
and depth, it could be a big enough area is a problem
too, but it has to all be in the same space. Okay,
so if you sell me land and there's a lot of little
pockets that are not tillable, I gotta live with that. But if
in one space there's a significant, you know, area even without height
that's not tillable, then that's a problem. All right, so that's what
he says.
Rabbi... so four קב kav within a space of five קב, kav,
that's a real, that's a real issue. רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן והוא שמובלעין ברובה של שדה. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan v'hu shemuvla'in b'ruba shel sadeh. No, no, no. He says
even if they are spread out, even if the majority, even if
the four קב kav is in, you know,
where's my green? So if this is the רוב השדה, rov hasadeh,
this is 60%, okay, and within that, you've got the four קב,
kav, you know, these little non-tillable spaces, okay, and they equal four
קב, kav, he says, and that's a problem. It's not even if
they're condensed, it's just too much of the land, okay? So it's
four קב kav within the majority of the field. But if, you
know, up to that, I'm sorry, up to that is tolerable, right?
More than that, right, if it was more than four קב kav
within the majority of the field, it would be a problem. Or
if it was four קב kav in the minority of the field,
or if it was four קב kav in 50% of the field,
that would be a problem. But up to four קב kav in
the majority of the field is okay. Any greater quantity or greater
density is not acceptable and you get your money back. Yeah.
Does the seller have an obligation to disclose? I mean, obviously the
seller knows the land. Does the seller have...
you mean if it's within the tolerable amount? That's a good question.
Like, if it's within the tolerable amount, so the sale will be
good regardless, right, does he still have the moral obligation to point
out, like, the problems of it? Or do we sort of say,
you know, you know, you know, look, that's the buyer's responsibility? It's
not my responsibility. But even if that's true legally, you're saying morally
does he have that obligation? So, you know, it's a really important
question to ask, which, you know, intuitively of course you would think
yes, right? But like that hasn't at all been discussed. What?
To what extent? Right. I mean, if it can be assumed that
when I say a field, it means a field with rocks here
and there. Right, I don't say, well we have a rock right
over
here, and another over there. Right, right,
right, right, right.
So maybe what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that when I
say basically בית כור עפר, Beis Kor Afar, right, I mean, you
know, that's what that is taken to mean, that up to...
you know. But let's say I'm selling you my house. And we
all know that every house, you know, has problems. Do I have
a responsibility to go through it and say, I want to tell
you exactly the problems we've got here, okay? There's a leak over
here, there's been some rot over there, there's been some whatever.
So in contemporary
reality, it's the buyer's responsibility to hire an engineer.
Right, right, so
that implies that you don't have.
So Rabbi I think is saying is we get that legally you
don't, is there some moral responsibility? They tell a story of the
חפץ חיים, Chofetz Chaim, I don't know if it's true, that you
know, he made his living by having like, he had a little
like a grocery, whatever, and he said he never made any money
because anytime anybody came in he said, wait, I want to show
you, this apple over here, it's got a little mark here, and
this thing over here it's got... so whatever.
But it's a good question. It's a good question. Okay, yeah.
So
maybe I'm visualizing this incorrectly. The people who are buying and selling,
I'm assuming that they're living within the same community, right, and that
they live with each other and they דאוון daven with each other
and their children are friends. So it's not as if somebody from
Scarsdale is buying something from Monsey...
right. But it's also not necessarily as intimate as you describe, but
it's true, you're right that sometimes the personal and the business are
not so separate. That's true. I hear the point. I want to
anyway, because Michael's not here I just want to, I mean unfortunately
he's not here but there was this line in the רשב״ם Rashbam
which says, right, when you have like exactly this, even if they're
not high, if it's too much untillable, it's a problem. The line
in the רשב״ם Rashbam is, he says, דהא בית כור עפר אתני
ליה ממכר לוקח, deha Beis Kor Afar atni leh mimkar lokeach, I'll
just read it to you, hold on, he says, דהא בית כור
עפר אתני ליה ממכר לוקח וכולי האי לא מחלי. deha Beis Kor
Afar atni leh mimkar lokeach v'chulei hai lo machli. Because basically you're
saying the word I'm selling you עפר afar which means tillable land.
So if too much is not tillable, that's a problem even if
it's not a separate space. But what the גמרא's Gemara saying is,
is it only if you look at it as a... unit? So
the first one said it's four קב kav within five קבין kavin
is
like that's up to that is okay, but any more, 4.1 קב
kav in five קבין kavin like that's a whole space that's not
tillable, that's a problem. And another, no, four קב kav in the
majority is okay, but if it was four קב kav in the
in the half of it, or you know, if it would be
more density than this, that would not be okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says now we have a
question. בעי רבי חייא ba'ei Rabbi Chiyya or רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba asks, רובן במיעוטא ומיעוטן ברובא מהו? ruban be-miyuta
ve-miyutan be-ruba mahu? Let's say the way the רשב״ם Rashbam reads it
is, let's say you take this majority, okay, and this majority is
not equally distributed. So you have four קב kav in this majority,
but here you've got like, you know, three קב kav right over
here,
okay? That's רובן במיעוטא, ruban be-miyuta, that's in a very small section
of the land. And then you've got like the rest over here.
So that's four קב kav in the majority, that's tolerable. Should we
say that's tolerable or should we say because you have this high
density in a certain location, that's not tolerable? So what do we
say? So תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Okay, בעי רבי ירמיה. ba'ei
Rabbi Yirmiah. Now רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiah asks, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiah
is always the one that likes asking these like, you know, I
don't know we might say nudnik-y questions, like he asks, you know,
but he likes asking these like, you know, speculative type positions. So
כשיר מהו? k'shir mahu? Let's say the untillable land is well, you've
got a picture right over there, let's say the untillable land is
all like a circle like this. So that makes it very hard
to sort of get around it, right? I mean, if my untillable
land is like this, you know, I'll manage, right? I'll plow this
way and I'll plow this way and I'll plow this way, you
know, I can basically even though I won't, you know, I can
sort of manage around it. But if it's sort of all defined
in this tight little circle, it makes it very hard, it makes
that space even more acceptable
unusable, so would that be a problem even if it's within four
קבין kavin within the right space? Okay, כשורא מהו? k'shura mahu? Let's
say it's in a line.
You know, so a line, you would say big deal, it's in
a line, that's perfect, I'll just till this way and this way
and I'll avoid it. But apparently the tilling would go in both
directions, that's at least what the רשב״ם Rashbam says, which is funny,
I didn't think that at all. So anyway, so he says if
they're scattered it's easier to move around it, but if they're all
in a line, you know, it's very hard to how are you
supposed to go in the other direction?
Okay, אצטדין מהו? itztadin mahu? Now אצטדין itztadin normally means a stadium,
but what the רשב״ם Rashbam says it means it means that they're
shaped like the horns of a stadium of like an ox that
would be, you know, sort of that you would do these like,
you know, what is it these bullfights like a bull. So he's
got a little picture there of horns of an ox, okay.
So דרך עקלתון מהו? derech akalton mahu? If it's a zigzag, you
know, is the configuration of this untillable land make it more of
a problem even if it's within except an acceptable density? So the
גמרא Gemara says on all those it says תיקו, teiku, we don't
know. Okay, תנא tanna אם
היה סלע יחידי אפילו כל שהוא אין נמדד עמה. im hayah sela
yechidi afilu kol shehu ein nimdad imah. If it is a single
rock, it's not counted with it. Now what do you mean every
rock is a single rock? Okay, so there's two interesting explanations. The
רשב״ם Rashbam says that what that means is that this rock, it's
a small rock, it's not a rock that normally would be a
big enough area or big enough height to be a problem, but
it's right here at the edge of the field. So it's not,
you know, using this word בטל, batel, it's not sort of like
בטל batel to the field, right? If it's right here at the
edge of the field like, you know, let's say that this was
a thing of the field, then I'm going to say, oh, excuse
me, my field is going to go like this. You don't get
to include something at the edge even if it is technically in
the borders of the field, but because it's at the edge, it's
not like incorporated into it. So even if it's not the right
even if it's like low enough and small enough, it's not a
big enough area to normally be a problem to not be counted,
if it's at the edge standing alone, then that gets sort of
pushed out, then you don't then you don't get to incorporate that
in the field. תוספות Tosafot says the word יחידי yechidi means something
different, it's got a name for itself. Oh yeah, that's Mike's rock,
we all go over there to Mike's rock, that's where we have
our picnics, we go onto Mike's rock over there, you know. Sometimes
you have that, like you have like little names for places. So
it's got a name to itself, that makes it separate and therefore
it's not incorporated. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. Okay, but
we'll read it the רשב״ם's Rashbam way. אם היה סלע
יחידי אפילו כל שהוא אין נמדד עמה. im hayah sela yechidi afilu
kol shehu ein nimdad imah. אם היה סמוך למצר אפילו כל שהוא
אין
נמדד עמה. im hayah samuch l'metzar afilu kol shehu ein nimdad imah.
So, oh wait, that's סמוך למצר. samuch l'metzar. So how did the
רשב״ם Rashbam say the difference between סלע יחידי? sela yechidi? Hold on,
that was סמוך למצר. samuch l'metzar. Did he incorporate the two or
did I make a mistake here? One minute.
No, he says סלע יחידי חוץ מן השדה סמוך לשדה. sela yechidi
chutz min hasadeh samuch l'sadeh.
So
I don't understand how he's
reading.
Yeah, they basically explain it the same way: adjacent to the field
boundary, outside the field boundary, outside. I guess the point is that
in this case, yeah, I don't see the big difference. But in
this case, it's like in the boundary but it's out by itself,
and the other case would be it's outside the boundary which would
be obviously much more obvious. So anyway, it's essentially, the רשב"א Rashba
explains the two of them to be essentially the same case. Okay?
סמוך למצר אפילו כל שהוא אין נמדדין עמה. samuch lemeitzar afilu kol
shehu ein nimdadin imah. But תוספות Tosafot says they're different: one is
at the edge and the other is it's got its own name.
So, בעי רב פפא. ba'ei Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav Pappa asked:
מושך עפר בינתים מהו? mushech afar beintayim mahu? Let's say there's a
little bit of dirt between
them. Meaning that it's not right at... like in this case, the
boundary would go like this.
Okay? It wouldn't be exactly at the boundary; there'd be a little
bit of dirt right over there. So I'm not just going to
say, like, okay,
don't count it with it, it's at the boundary of the field.
No, no, no. Not totally exactly up against the line. So maybe
I do get to incorporate it into the field. מושך עפר בינתים
מהו? mushech afar beintayim mahu? תיקו, teiku, we don't
know. בעי רב אשי. ba'ei Rav Ashi. רב אשי Rav Ashi asked:
עפר מלמטה וצונמא מלמעלה, afar milmata vetsunma milmala, let's say there's dirt
below and rock
above, or
עפר מלמעלה וצונמא מלמטה. afar milmala vetsunma milmata. מהו? mahu?
תיקו. teiku. So what does that mean? That means one of two
scenarios. One is, at the top it looks like it's exactly along
the edge, and then we said it's אין נמדדין עמה. ein nimdadin
imah. But if you actually looked underground, the rock is sort of
wider at the top and narrower at the bottom, right?
So, here, try to do a cross-section, okay? So here, at the
top, right, it looks like it's exactly along the edge. But if
you dig underneath, you'll see that there's actually dirt between the bottom
of the rock and the edge, so to see what I'm trying
to draw? Okay. Or the reverse, right? That at the top there's
a
space,
right? But it spreads out at the bottom. So, and then this
is all filled with dirt, right? So at the top there's space
between it and the borderline, but at the bottom it's right up
against the borderline. So what do you say there? And all that
the גמרא Gemara ends with תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Okay, so
all these different ways in which the rock is not incorporated into
the field. Let's move on to the next משנה. mishnah.
The distinction he was making was that the
boundary was along the boundary but within it as opposed to along
the boundary and outside of it.
Yeah. Okay. Okay, fine. We got the idea though.
Let's look at the next משנה. mishnah. בית כור אני מוכר לך
מידה בחבל. beit kor ani mocher lecha mida bechevel. All right,
now we're dealing with... so before we were saying you measure the
whole field and there was this problem in it, do you go
ahead and adjust the what do you call it, adjust the
price accordingly. Now we have a case where I sell you, I'm
going to sell you this בית כור beit kor מידה בחבל. mida
bechevel. By the measured, like by the
rope. Meaning like by the ruler. So I use the word to
tell you it's going to be precise. I'm selling you a
בית כור beit kor measured by the ruler. So in that case,
פיחת כל שהוא ינכה. pichat kol shehu yinakeh. Now, my field is
my field. It's not like you could imagine like I got wide
open acreage and let's just go and we'll measure out an acre
and that'll be yours. No, I've got a field and I'm telling
you it's a בית כור beit kor and I'm telling you precise
measurement. So now we go and we actually measure the field I
sold you and it's a little bit off. Okay, so because I
said the words precise measurement, so פיחת כל שהוא ינכה. pichat kol
shehu yinakeh. So if it's a little smaller, I have to reduce
the price. הותיר כל שהוא יחזיר. hotir kol shehu yachzir. If it's
a little bit larger, יחזיר, yachzir, then the buyer has to give
me back
either the appropriate money or maybe a little bit of land. We'll
see. Okay. ואם אמר הן חסר הן יתר. ve'im amar hen chaser
hen yeter. Now, but what if I tell you I'm selling you
my field, you see it, it's right in front of you, you
could bring out an engineer, measure it for yourself or whatever, but
I'm telling you more or less it's a בית כור. beit kor.
All right, so but I say the word more or less. I'm
signaling to you that it's not exact; it might not be exactly
that size. So how much sort of wiggle room does that give
us? הן חסר הן יתר אפילו פיחת רובע לסאה או הותיר רובע
לסאה הגיעו. hen chaser hen yeter afilu pichat rova leseah o hotir
rova leseah higio. So I can be off by a quarter of
a קב kav to a סאה. seah. All right, so there are
six, a quarter of a קב. kav. Hear this once again. Okay.
There are six קב kav to a סאה, seah, so if I
could be off a quarter of a קב kav per סאה, seah,
I could be off by one twenty-fourth.
Right? You see that? A quarter of a קב, kav, if there
are six קב kav to a סאה, seah, I could be off
by one twenty-fourth. Okay, now, that's per unit of land. All right,
so if it's a בית כור, beis kor, whatever, you just multiply
how much that would be,
but basically, that's the ratio. Okay, now, דאמרי
היכא
דחסרון ויתרה אפילו פחת רבע לסאה או הותיר רבע לסאה הגיעו, de-amrei
heicha de-chesron ve-yetra afilu pachat rova le-seah o hotir rova le-seah higiyu,
יותר מכאן, yoseir mikan, if it's more, יעשה חשבון, ya'aseh cheshbon, then
you have to figure it out, then you have to reimburse. Okay,
whichever side got more than that or less than that. מה הוא
מחזיר? mah hu machzir? Now, let's say here I'm selling it to
Eli, okay? And it was less than I expected. I said a
בית כור beis kor and
it really wound up being, right, a little less than a בית
כור, beis kor, less than this one twenty-fourth. It was even, I
said more or less, but it was off, you know, even even
more than that.
So how do we reconcile that? He paid me a thousand dollars
for it, he figured it was going to be one acre, it
wound up being, I don't know, 0.8 acres, off much more than
the tolerable amount. So what's going to happen? He got less than
he than he expected, so there's only one solution right now, which
is what? What do I have to do?
I sold him an acre for a thousand dollars, it's 0.8 acres.
Give him some money back.
There's only one point, I can give him his money back. Right,
but we're assuming, right, if I had more land I could just
add to it, but we're assuming it's only one plot. Okay, so
the only thing I can do if it's one plot of land
is give him his money back. So if he got less and
too much less than he was expecting, not within the tolerable amount,
I give him his money back.
Let's say it's... You mean the money for the area that he
didn't get or the whole of the money?
No, the money for the area he didn't get. So if it's
like a thousand dollars for an acre and he got 0.8 acres,
I give him back two hundred dollars. Okay, that's what there's only
solution, assuming that it's only one plot of land. Let's say, however,
he got much more than the tolerable amount, even when I said
more less. So he got 1.2 acres. So there's two possible solutions
here. What are the two possible solutions?
Either he gives me the land back or the money.
Either he gives me the 0.2 acres back or he gives me
the money back. Which do you think it should be? The money.
What? Okay, why do you think the money?
Well, you could have made a mistake, then you have a choice
if you want to
give him the land back or not. Right, so the question is,
so let's see what the משנה mishnah says. The משנה mishnah says
מה הוא מחזיר? mah hu machzir? What is Eli going to give
back to me? So it says מה הוא מחזיר לו מעות, mah
hu machzir lo ma'os, money. ואם
רצה מחזיר לו קרקע, ve-im ratzah machzir lo karka, then land. So
the obvious question is, if who wants? Okay, so what the רשב"ם
Rashbam says is it means if I want, because if it's really
again one plot of land, what the heck am I going to
do with 0.2 acres? That's completely unusable. So in that type of
a case, even though really he should be giving me back the
0.2 acres because I sold him one acre, I didn't sell you
these 0.2, it was a mistake, give it back to me, okay,
but nevertheless they did not demand that I take that back because
I can't use that. And they actually said that I can just
get the extra money from him. Now of course you could say
I could wind up cheating him. I want to sell 1.2 acres,
I'm going to tell him it's one, he's going to buy it,
and then he wouldn't have bought 1.2 acres because he didn't that
was outside of his budget. But now he thought he was one
acre he could afford it, now he's got to cough up another
two hundred dollars. Okay, but the point is like, you know what,
you could have measured it also yourself before we went into this
transaction, which gets back to that. So is it could he sometimes
the buyer find himself in an uncomfortable situation that he has to
pay out more money and buy a larger plot than he was
expecting? That might be, but you know, he can take precautions as
well. So in this case, he gives me back money, but if
I want to I can ask for the land back. One minute.
ולמה אמרו, velamah amru, so why did they say מחזיר לו מעות,
machzir lo ma'os, give me money? ליפות כחו של מוכר, liyafot kocho
shel mocher, in order to improve my standing because what am I
supposed to do with a little slice of land? אם ששייר בשדה
בית תשעה קבין, im she-shiyer basadeh beis tishah kabin, now we're going
to say that it is possible that it was so off that
the plot of land would not be so small and the plot
and that he actually and I cannot demand money, that he's entitled
to give me back the plot of land. What plot of land
is considered big enough to be a little plot, you know, big
enough for like a mini field for growing
wheat? So now it's going to tell you the following minimum sizes.
If you were off by this amount, then I cannot demand money,
then he can force to give me this back because it is
a usable plot. What would be the size of a usable plot?
So בשדה בית תשעה קבין, basadeh beis tishah kabin, by a field
nine kav, בגינה בית חצי קב, begina beis chatzi kav, a vegetable
garden half a kav, וכדברי רבי עקיבא בית רובע, ukedivrei Rabi Akiva
beis rova, and Rabbi Akiva would say a quarter of a kav.
So in those cases, מחזיר לו את הקרקע, machzir lo es hakarka,
then he can force the land back on me even if I
don't want it because he could say, hey buddy. I know you
like big plots of land, but this is big enough to be
used and it's a, it's a usable land and I'm giving it
back to you. I never bought this. Okay. And then it says
ולא את הרובע בלבד הוא מחזיר אלא את כל המותר. velo et
harova bilvad hu machazir ela et kol hamotar. It's not only the
רובע rova meaning not only the overage that he's returning, but he's
returning the entire amount, right? If it was off by whatever we
said, it was off by point two, it was off by 2%,
he would not have had to give me back anything. If it's
off by 2.5%,
he doesn't just give me back 0.5%. He gives back the whole
2.5%. That was the concept we had before. You had a question?
I just wondered linguistically whether that was where the phrase may the
buyer should the buyer
Yeah, clearly, it's exactly this question. Yeah, you have a responsibility and
so on. Okay, so I just want to do one last little
math thing, okay? Because a בית כור beit kor so how big
is, how big is if you're off by this amount by one
twenty-fourth? Okay, so if you're so how much is that for if
you're off by four קב kav per סאה se'ah or no what
did we say it was? Four קב kav per סאה, se'ah, right?
No, what did we say it was? I'm sorry. רובע. rova. A
quarter of a קב kav per סאה. se'ah. So you can be
off by a quarter of a קב kav per סאה. se'ah. There
are thirty סאה se'ah in a בית כור. beit kor. So you
would be off in a בית כור beit kor thirty quarter קבים,
kavs, thirty times a quarter is thirty quarters, anybody, seven and a
half. So if you're off by a quarter קב kav per סאה,
se'ah, you're off by seven and a half קב kav for a
בית כור. beit kor. Now and nine קב kav is usable land.
So when is Eli entitled, when is Eli entitled, when am I
able to sort of say give it back to me, I gave
you too much? Once it's over seven and a half קב. kav.
From that point until nine קב kav I can choose to get
the money back or the land. But once it's already nine קב
kav over, which is not a big difference, right, then Eli can
say, look, this is already usable land, take this land back. Okay,
so that's the point at the end of the משנה. Mishna. So
we'll continue with this tomorrow.